Finding Aid for William DeKleine papers, 1914-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William DeKleine papers 1914-1955
DeKleine, William, 1877-1957.
3 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851117 Aa 2; UAm
Physician, public health officer, medical director of the American Red Cross and Michigan Health Commissioner, 1944-1947. Correspondence, articles, speeches, and other professional papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. William DeKleine (donor no. 3222 ) and came to the library in 1956-1957.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William DeKleine was born November 28, 1877 in Jamestown, Michigan. He was a graduate of Hope College, Northwestern University, and the University of Michigan School of Public Health. He practiced medicine in Grand Haven, Michigan from 1906 to 1914. He next directed the tuberculosis survey campaign for the Michigan Board of Health from 1915 to 1917. He served as health officer of Flint, Mich., from 1917 to 1922, and of Saginaw, from 1922 to 1925.
DeKleine directed the child health demonstration at Mansfield, Ohio, under the American Child Health Association in 1925, and under the Commonwealth Fund at Fargo, N.D., in 1926-27, and at Salem, Ore., the next year. DeKleine became associated with the American Red Cross in 1927 during the Mississippi flood. From 1928 to 1942, DeKleine was Medical Director of the Red Cross and supervised medical and public health work in areas stricken by floods, tornadoes, fires, drought and other disasters. This included the Southern floods of 1929 and 1939, the drought in Arkansas and other states in 1931, aftermaths of tornadoes in Alabama and other states in 1932 and after the New London (Tex.) school disaster in 1937. From 1944 to 1947, DeKleine was State Health Commissioner of Michigan. For the remainder of his life, he returned to private practice. He died September 20, 1957.
The William DeKleine papers have been arranged into the following series: Biographical; Correspondence; Other papers: research interests and writings; Red Cross materials; Articles and speeches; and Photographs. Some of the correspondents in the collection include: Paul DeKruif, Harry F. Kelly, John H. Kellogg, Charles S. Mott, Arnold Mulder, Chase S. Osborn, and Kim Sigler. Some of the topics covered in the collection include medical relief, pellagra research, and the work of the Red Cross. There are also histories he wrote on the Good Roads Movement in western Michigan and the First Presbyterian Church of Lansing, Michigan.
Subjects:
First Presbyterian Church (Lansing, Mich.); Lansing (Mich.); Medicine--Michigan.; Michigan. Dept. of Health.; Pellagra.; Physicians--Michigan.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Lansing.; Public health--United States.; Red Cross and Red Crescent--Michigan.; Roads--Michigan.; Soya Corporation of America.; DeKleine, William, 1877-1957.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings--Michigan--Flint.; Dwellings--Michigan--Flint; Physicians--Michigan.; Poor persons.; Public health--Michigan.; Slums--Michigan--Flint.; DeKleine, William, 1877-1957.
Contributors:
De Kruif, Paul, 1890-1971.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.; Mulder, Arnold, 1885-1959.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Portraits.
- Biographical
  - Biographical materials, 1928-1950 and undated (Box 1)
  - Memoir, undated
    - [Chapters 1-4] (Box 1)
    - [Chapters 5-9] (Box 1)
    - [Chapters 10-13] (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1914-May 1947, 33 folders (Box 1)
  - June 1947-1955, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Other papers: research interests and writings
  - Reports, memoranda, etc., undated and 1905-1947, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Printed materials, 1937-1947 and undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Research papers, 1930-1949 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning pellagra, 1930-1949, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Flint Health Department, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Selective Service System (health concerns), 1939-1943 (Box 2)
  - History of the Good Roads Movement in western Michigan (Box 2)
  - History of the First Presbyterian Church of Lansing (Box 2)
  - History of the Red Cross Blood Procurement Program for the Army and Navy in World War II (Box 2)
  - Holland Club of Washington, D. C. miscellanea, 1942-1944 (Box 2)
- Red Cross materials
  - Undated and 1929-1931, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1932-1941, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Articles and speeches
  - 1924-1946 and undated, 15 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize folder)
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Groups (Box 3)
  - Flint slums, ca. 1920, 2 folders (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
DeKruif, Paul, 1890-1971.
1937-1942; 1944-1947
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
Apr. 23, 1922
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.
1944; Apr. 25, 1947
Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.
Apr. 1, 1941; Apr. 24, 1942; Oct. 13, 1943; Apr. 11, 1944
Mulder, Arnold, 1885-1959.
1937; 1939; 1944; 1946-1953; 1955
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.
Dec. 2, 1919
Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.
1947